ここでいいのかい？
This is fine?
寮[りょう]:hostel/dormitory|bureau (government department beneath a ministry under the ritsuryo system), 寮[つかさ]:office|chief|(Yaeyama Islands in Okinawa) person (usually a woman) whose duty it is to officiate at religions ceremonies, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
寮まで回ってあげるよ
I can take you to the dorm.
Oh, I want to stop by somewhere first.
寄る[よる]:to approach|to gather (in one place)|to stop by (while on one's way to another place)||
あっ ちょっと寄りたいとこがあって
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, お世話になる[おせわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted
ホント お世話になりました
Thank you so much for everything.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
いえいえ こちらこそ
No, thank you!
人手[ひとで, ヒトデ]:starfish/sea star|northern Pacific seastar (Asterias amurensis), 人手[ひとで]:someone else's hands|hand (worker)|labor|, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
また人手が必要になったらお願いするわ
I'll call you the next time we need help.
You'd still ask me,
even after I made that huge mistake?
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
あんなに失敗したのに 俺なんかでいいんですか？
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, へこむ:to be dented/to be indented|to be overwhelmed, まくる:to turn up/to roll up (e.g. sleeves)|to do relentlessly
あんなに失敗してへこみまくったんだもの
You got so depressed afterwards.
I'm sure you'll be really
careful next time.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 慎重[しんちょう]:careful/cautious/prudent, やってくれる:to come along/to come around|to arrive at the present
次は慎重にやってくれるっしょ？
Don't beat yourself up for
making one mistake, okay?
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
１回失敗したくらいで
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
「俺なんか」なんて言っちゃ駄目よ
See you!
したらね！
I wish I'd been born into your family.
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead, 子供[こども]:child/children, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born
俺 御影んちの子供に生まれたかったぁ
Caution:
Cow Crossing
I haven't seen him in almost a month.
カ月[かげつ]:months (period of), 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
１カ月近く会ってないからなー
Pig Pen
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
あいつ 元気にしてるかな？
I wonder how he's doing.
こんにちはー
Hello!
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
豚丼が豚になってる！
Pork Bowl's turned into a pig!
He's always been a pig, Hachiken-kun!
元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
元から豚だよ 八軒君
But he's gotten so fat and
flabby in just a month...
たった:only/merely/but, カ月[かげつ]:months (period of), ぶくぶく:bulging/swelling (e.g. with water)|bubbling
たった１カ月でこんなだるっだるのぶくぶくに
Pigs sure grow fast.
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 成長[せいちょう]:growth/grow to adulthood, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, パネェ:a lot/to a very great extent/absolutely
豚の成長速度パネェ
Stop calling pigs fat and flabby!
ぶくぶく:bulging/swelling (e.g. with water)|bubbling
だるだるのぶくぶくとバカにするな
The body fat percentage
of pigs is about 15%.
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 脂肪[しぼう]:fat/grease/blubber, 率[りつ]:rate/ratio/proportion, 前後[ぜんご]:front and rear|before and after|order||, 前後[まえしりえ]:front and rear/front and back/before and behind
豚の体脂肪率は１５％前後
対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||
対して
In comparison,
men average about 10-20%,
平均[へいきん, へいぎん]:average/mean|balance
人間の男の平均は１０～２０
Average Human Male
and women average about 20-30%!
女は２０～３０だ
Average Human Female
I'm a bigger pig than
pigs themselves...
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
私 豚より豚だわ…
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
豚なんて言って ごめん 豚丼
I'm sorry I called you
a pig, Pork Bowl...
Wait, which one's Pork Bowl?
どいつ:who?, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
って どいつが豚丼だよ
あっ いた
Oh, there he is...
He hasn't changed.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
変わってないね この子
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
ったく そんなお人よしでどうすんだよ
Man... Why are you so considerate?
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 食い[くい]:eating|bite (in fishing), 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
この豚は食いが悪いな
This pig doesn't eat enough.
At this rate,
体重[たいじゅう]:body weight/one's weight, 不足[ふそく]:insufficiency/shortage/deficiency, 等外[とうがい]:also-ran/non-winner
このままだと体重不足で等外だ
he'll be rated off-grade
for being too light.
Off-grade?
等外[とうがい]:also-ran/non-winner
等外？
枝肉[えだにく]:dressed carcass/meat on the bone, 取引[とりひき]:transactions/dealings/business, 規格[きかく]:standard/norm, 極上[ごくじょう]:first-rate/finest quality/the best, 並[なみ]:average|line|mid-grade|, 等外[とうがい]:also-ran/non-winner, 格付け[かくづけ, かくずけ]:rating/classification/allocation
枝肉の取引規格には極上・上・中・並・等外と格付けがあって
Pork carcasses are evaluated
and graded super premium, premium,
medium, standard, or off-grade.
価格[かかく]:price/value/cost, 直結[ちょっけつ]:direct connection/online/on-line
それが価格に直結する
The pig's grade determines its sell price.
Off-grade carcasses will only
fetch a mediocre price.
等外[とうがい]:also-ran/non-winner, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case), 値[あたい, ね]:price|value|value|, 値[ち]:level/value, 付く[つく]:to be attached|to remain imprinted|to bear (fruit, interest, etc.)||, 付く[づく]:to become (a state, condition, etc.)
等外ではあってないような値しか付かん
八軒君？
Hachiken-kun?
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
さあ 食えよ
C'mon, eat.
本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged, 夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 日差し[ひざし]:sunlight/rays of the sun
本格的な夏の日差しが
肌[はだ, はだえ]:skin|body (in the context of intimate bodily contact)|surface|, 焦がす[こがす]:to burn/to scorch/to singe, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
肌を焦がしていく様に
恋焦がれる[こいこがれる]:to yearn for/to pine/to be deeply in love with
私もあなたに恋焦がれる
海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, ドライブ:drive/trip by car/driving, 運転[うんてん]:operation (of a machine, etc.)|driving|working (capital, etc.)
海へドライブ 運転するよ
横顔[よこがお]:face in profile/profile/face seen from the side, 撫でる[なでる]:to stroke/to caress|to comb (hair), 潮風[しおかぜ]:salty sea breeze/salt wind, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
横顔撫でる 潮風が気持ちいいsummer day
la la la summer day
ビーチパラソル:beach parasol/beach umbrella, カラフル:colorful/colourful
ビーチパラソルカラフルだ yeah
砂浜[すなはま]:sandy beach, 咲く[さく]:to bloom, 花[はな]:flower|cherry blossom|beauty||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
砂浜に咲く 花みたい
KISS YOU あなたの心
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
もっともっと近くにいたい 感じたい
私だけ見て
膨らむ[ふくらむ]:to expand/to swell (out)/to get big
KISS YOU ぐっと膨らんだ
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 唇[くちびる]:lips, のせる:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride/to give a lift, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
胸の思い 唇にのせて 伝えたいと
だから KISS YOU
だから さあ KISS YOU
Episode 9
Hachiken
Hesitates over Pork Bowl
We're back!
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
ただいまでーす
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
戻りましたー
We've returned!
Hey, Aikawa.
よお 相川
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you), 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 焼ける[やける]:to burn/to be roasted|to be jealous
久しぶり あれ？ 少し焼けた？
Been a while!
Oh, did you get a tan?
I was working the whole time.
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), バイト:work (esp. part time or casual)
ずっとバイトしてたから
カ月[かげつ]:months (period of), 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
１カ月会わないとみんな変わるなぁ
After a month,
everyone looks different.
Aikawa, Hachiken, welcome back.
おかえり:return|welcome home
相川 八軒 おかえり
おー
Thanks.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
ただいま
Who's that?
誰？ あれ
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl
あんな女子いたっけ？
Did we have any girls like that?
It's been a while.
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
久しぶり
Tama-chan, you've lost a lot of weight!
痩せる[やせる]:to become thin/to lose weight|to be barren
多摩ちゃん 痩せたねぇ
The summer heat got to me.
夏バテ[なつばて, なつバテ]:suffering from summer heat/summer heat fatigue
ちょっと夏バテしちゃって
多摩子！？
Tamako?!
痩せる[やせる]:to become thin/to lose weight|to be barren
痩せたっていうか トランスフォームだよねぇ
It's more like a transformation
than weight loss...
Yo!
Ｙｏ！ 八軒 相川 久しぶりー
Hachiken, Aikawa, long time no see!
Who're you?
誰？
常盤だＹｏ
It's Tokiwa!
What's one plus one?
１＋１は？
Three!
３！
常盤だ
It's Tokiwa, all right.
What's with the mohawk?
とさか:cockscomb/crest, 鶏[にわとり, とり]:(domestic) chicken|chicken (meat), リスペクト:respect
何だ そのとさか 鶏リスペクト！？
Is that chicken respect?
Wha? Tokiwa?
えっ？ 常盤？
常盤なの？
Is that Tokiwa?
Everyone seems surprised
by my transformation.
変化[へんか]:change|variety|inflection|, 変化[へんげ]:shapeshifting (of an animal or spirit)|incarnation|transformation, 驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished
みんな俺の変化に驚いているようだな
So this is what they mean by
summer break transformation.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, デビュー:debut
これが夏休みデビューってやつか
初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
初めて見た
He's the first one I've seen.
I didn't know it existed.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ホントにいるんだ
Shut up! Girls should stay quiet—
黙る[だまる]:to be silent, 子ども[こども]:child/children
うっさい！ 黙れ 女子ども！
めんこい:dear/darling/adorable
ななな…何あれ！？ あのめんこいの！
Wh-Wh-Wh-Who is that hottie?!
Huh? Which one?
はっ？ どれ？
That one! That girl!
あれ！ あの女！
She's about Tamako's height,
with the same hair color!
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 身長[しんちょう]:height (of body)/stature, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 髪[かみ]:hair (on the head), 色[いろ]:colour|complexion|appearance||, 色[しょく]:counter for colours
多摩子くらいの身長で多摩子みたいな髪の色の！
あぁ…
Well...
Oh, been a while, Komaba.
駒場[こまば]:pasture used for grazing horses (esp. ponies), 久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
あら 駒場 久しぶり
痩せる[やせる]:to become thin/to lose weight|to be barren
おぉ 多摩子か 痩せたな お前
Oh, Tamako!
You lost weight.
野球部[やきゅうぶ]:baseball club (i.e. baseball team of a university, corporation, etc.), ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising
野球部はずっと練習だったの？
Was the baseball club
training non-stop?
Yeah, it was either
training or away games.
練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising, 遠征[えんせい]:expedition/campaign|away series, ばっか:only/merely|approximately
おー 練習と遠征ばっかだったわ
Did you grow more muscle?
さらに:furthermore/again/after all, 筋肉[きんにく]:muscle/sinew, 筋肉[すじにく]:sinewy meat
さらに筋肉ついたんじゃないの？
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
お前はそんなに変わってないのな
I guess you haven't
changed that much, huh?
よし
Okay!
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
失礼しまーす
Excuse me.
Oh, Sensei, sorry to bother you.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
あ… すいません 先生
I'd like to talk to
you about something.
相談[そうだん]:consultation/discussion
ちょっと相談なんですけど
8/22 (Thu)
Opening Ceremony
All right, everyone's here.
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 揃う[そろう]:to become complete|to be equal|to gather
よーし みんな揃ってるな？
Looks like everyone had a safe break.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
夏休み中は事故もなく
Actually, some of you look
like you had too much fun.
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting), 満喫[まんきつ]:having enough of (food, drink, etc.)/having one's fill|fully enjoying, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
事故どころか 休みを満喫し過ぎている者もいるようだな
Tokiwa.
起立[きりつ]:standing up
常盤 起立
Stand up.
持ち物[もちもの]:one's property/personal effects/one's belongings, アクセサリー:accessory, 服装[ふくそう]:garments/attire, 髪[かみ]:hair (on the head)
持ち物 アクセサリー 服装 髪
Belongings! Accessories! Clothes! Hair!
That's a counted yakuman!
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 役満[やくまん]:win worth 32000 points (or, if dealer, 48000 points)
数え役満だ
I'm going to bring you up at the staff
meeting for disciplinary action.
処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal), 職員[しょくいん]:staff member/personnel, 会議[かいぎ]:meeting/conference/session, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
処分について職員会議にかける
えええっ！
What?!
浮かれる[うかれる]:to make merry/to be festive, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by, 羽目を外す[はめをはずす, ハメをはずす]:to cut loose/to act without restraint, 休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting)
浮かれ過ぎて羽目を外すなと休み前に言ったはずだぞ
I warned all of you before break not
to get too excited and carried away.
相応[そうおう]:suitability/fitness, 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, 覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
それ相応の罰は覚悟しているだろうな？
You'd better be prepared
for disciplinary action.
Um...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 停学[ていがく]:suspension from school, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
えっ…まさか停学なんてないっすよね
You're not gonna suspend me, right?
停学[ていがく]:suspension from school, 生ぬるい[なまぬるい]:lukewarm|half-hearted|lenient
停学など生ぬるい
Suspension would be too good
for the likes of you.
Library
Recreation Room
Stress and Development
常盤 どうした？
How's Tokiwa?
He's still tearfully cutting
his hair in the bathroom.
風呂[ふろ]:bath|bathroom|room for drying lacquerware|, 涙[なみだ, なだ]:tear/tears|sympathy, 断髪式[だんぱつしき]:retirement ceremony of a wrestler where his top-knot is cut
まだ風呂で涙の断髪式やってるぞ
What you lookin' at?
何見てんだ？
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 太る[ふとる]:to grow fat (stout, plump)/to become fat/to gain weight
うん… 豚丼 もう少し太らせたいんだけど
Well, I want to get Pork Bowl
a little bit fatter,
方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
何かいい方法ないかなって
so I'm trying to find
a good way to do that.
I think Tomoizawa's
family runs a pig farm.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 巴[ともえ]:huge comma design, 沢[さわ]:swamp/marsh|mountain stream, 養豚[ようとん]:pig-keeping/pig farming
確か 巴沢んち 養豚だべ
Hey, Tomoizawa!
おーい:hey!/oi!|I, 巴[ともえ]:huge comma design, 沢[さわ]:swamp/marsh|mountain stream
おーい 巴沢
Yeah?
何？
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 太る[ふとる]:to grow fat (stout, plump)/to become fat/to gain weight
八軒が豚丼太らせたいんだと
Hachiken wants to fatten up Pork Bowl.
餌[えさ, え]:(animal) feed/fodder|bait, 食い[くい]:eating|bite (in fishing), 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
何かあいつだけ餌の食いが悪くて
He's the only one who's
not eating well...
A-ha.
ほう
出荷[しゅっか]:shipping/outgoing freight/forwarding, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 仕上げる[しあげる]:to finish up/to complete/to finish off, 秘策[ひさく]:secret plan or measures
出荷までに豚を仕上げる秘策を知りたいと？
So you want to know a
secret strategy to finish
a pig before it's shipped out?
Y-Yeah. Is there one?
方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
おっ…おう 何か方法があるのか？
We use liquid feed!
ずばり:decisively/decidedly|precisely
うちはずばり水溶き
Liquid feed?
水溶き？
Dairy Science
Hey, bad news!
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal), たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
大変 大変 常盤の処分が出たって
They decided on the disciplinary
action for Tokiwa!
What's it going to be?
処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal)
処分って…
Don't tell me he's suspended!
嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|, 退学[たいがく]:dropping out of school|expulsion from school|leaving school (university, etc.) after completing a course
嘘！？ 退学！？
Man, I knew it.
やっぱり:too/also|still
ああ やっぱりな
You're lucky it's just one
week of forced labor.
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|, じゃん:isn't it, 強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party
１週間で済んでよかったじゃん 強制労働
Damn it... I only went
outta line a little bit.
はっちゃける:to make merry and forget one's troubles/to do as one pleases, じゃん:isn't it
チクショー ちょっとはっちゃけただけじゃんかよ
はっちゃける:to make merry and forget one's troubles/to do as one pleases, 過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much), っつー:meaning/called/said
はっちゃけ過ぎだっつーの
Way outta line.
卒業[そつぎょう]:graduation/completion (e.g. of a course)|outgrowing something, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
お前 卒業させてもらえなくなるぞ
They won't let you graduate
if you don't stop.
赤点[あかてん]:failing mark (e.g. in exam), だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood)
ただでさえ赤点だらけなのによ
You're already failing tests, anyway.
Uh... Crap!
ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific
うわぁ ヤバい
Huh?
あれ？
あぁ
Why are you here?
何で八軒がいるの？
It isn't forced labor, is it?
強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party
強制労働…じゃないよな？
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 出荷[しゅっか]:shipping/outgoing freight/forwarding, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 世話[せわ]:looking after/help/aid, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, ことにする:to make a distinction/to differ/to be different, ことにする:to decide to|to pretend that
うん…先生に頼んで出荷まで豚丼の世話させてもらうことにした
Uh, I asked the teachers to let me
take care of Pork Bowl until
it's time to send him off.
I see.
気に入る[きにいる]:to be pleased with/to suit
そっかー お前 あいつ 気に入ってたもんな
You've always liked him.
好く[すく]:to like/to love/to be fond of, 好く[よく]:nicely/properly|frequently, 実習[じっしゅう]:practice/practising/training (esp. practical and hands-on), 増やす[ふやす]:to increase/to add to/to augment
つーか何好きこのんで実習増やしてんだ
Wait, why're you choosing to
increase your practicum hours?
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 世話[せわ]:looking after/help/aid, 余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, 別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell, 切ない[せつない]:painful/heartrending|oppressive, じゃん:isn't it
最後まで世話したら余計に別れが切なくなるじゃん
If you take care of him
until the very end,
it'll be even harder for
you when it's time.
後悔[こうかい]:regret/repentance/remorse
うん でもここで何もしないと何か後悔しそうだし
Yeah.
But if I don't do something now,
I think I'll regret it.
I thought I might figure
something out...
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
もしかしたら何か見えてくるんじゃないかなって
Oh! Then maybe you can stand in
for me on my forced labor duty.
強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party, 肩代わり[かたがわり]:taking over another's debt/shouldering someone else's burden/subrogation, ことにする:to make a distinction/to differ/to be different, ことにする:to decide to|to pretend that
あっ じゃあ 俺の強制労働八軒が肩代わりするってことにすれば
Oh, come on...
お前なあ
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 反省[はんせい]:reflection/reconsideration|regret
ホント反省ねえな
You are shameless.
卒業[そつぎょう]:graduation/completion (e.g. of a course)|outgrowing something, 強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party, なさる:to do
卒業まで強制労働してなさい
You should be stuck with forced
labor till you graduate!
えっ？ えっ？
What're you doing?
何やってんだ？
溶く[とく]:to dissolve (paint)/to scramble (eggs)/to melt (metal, etc.), 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
うん 水で溶くとよく食うって聞いて
Oh, I heard they eat more when
you mix the feed with water.
Oh, really?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
へえー ホントかよ？
It's time-consuming,
手間[てま]:time/labour/labor, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
手間かかるけど
出荷[しゅっか]:shipping/outgoing freight/forwarding, 体重[たいじゅう]:body weight/one's weight, 増やす[ふやす]:to increase/to add to/to augment, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
出荷前に体重増やしたいときやるらしい
but they do it to fatten up the pigs
before sending them off.
Here's my special blend!
特製[とくせい]:special make/deluxe, ブレンド:blend
さあ 八軒さま特製ブレンドだ
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛っ
八軒？
Hachiken?
Sorry.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
悪い
まだ３時すぎだぞ
It's three in the morning.
部活[ぶかつ]:club activities
部活の前にちょっとやることあってさ
There's something I have to do
before my club duties!
よーし:alright/all right/right on, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
よーし いっぱい食えよ
All right, eat up!
体重[たいじゅう]:body weight/one's weight, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
なっ…お前らは体重足りてるだろ
You guys are big enough!
Fine!
順番[じゅんばん]:turn (in line)/order of things/sequential order, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
分かったよ 順番に行くから 待ってろ 豚ども
You'll get your turn, so wait, pigs!
Oh, good morning!
おう おはよー
How long have you been here?!
いつからやってんの？
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop
あっ ヤベッ！ 馬！
Oh, crap!
The horses!
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 戻ってくる[もどってくる]:to come back
また後で戻ってくるから
I'll be back later!
Pigs, horses...
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, 満喫[まんきつ]:having enough of (food, drink, etc.)/having one's fill|fully enjoying
豚だ 馬だと エゾノーを満喫してるな あいつ
He's really drinking
in Ezonoo life, huh?
Why is he doing all this?
何でそこまですんだ？
Because he named the pig, of course.
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
名前なんて付けるからだろ
But I too used to name cows as a kid.
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
でも俺も小さいころ牛に名前付けてたなぁ
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob
そういえば 私も連れていかれるとき泣いたわ
Now that I think about it,
I used to cry when they
got taken away, too.
Basically, we just got used to it.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 慣れる[なれる]:to get used to|to become skilled in|to become tame
結局は慣れだろ？
いつごろ:about when/how soon, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 食用[しょくよう]:for use as food/edible, 区別[くべつ]:distinction/differentiation/classification
いつごろからペットと食用の区別ってついてた？
When'd you start knowing the difference
between animals as pets
and animals as food?
Cafeteria
I'm starving...
腹[はら]:abdomen|womb|one's mind||, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate
腹減った
Huh?!
Hachiken
Yuugo
掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting, 当番[とうばん]:being on duty, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty
掃除当番忘れてた！ ヤベえ！ 罰当番…！
Crap, I forgot I had cleaning duty!
I'm gonna get detention chores!
Oh, I took care of it for you.
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
俺 代わりにやっといたぞ
Huh?
掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
八軒 掃除の時間に帰ってこなかっただろ
You didn't come back for
cleaning duty, right?
I did it for you.
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
代わりにやっといた
Beppu-sama...
別府さま！
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 当番[とうばん]:being on duty, 代わる[かわる]:to succeed|to take the place of|to be exchanged
今度俺が当番のとき代わってね
Just do it for me when it's my turn.
I'm going ahead.
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
お先に失礼しまーす
Good job!
お疲れさま[おつかれさま]:thank you/many thanks|that's enough for today
お疲れさま～
Isn't he getting more
run down every day?
弱る[よわる]:to weaken/to be troubled/to be downcast
何か日に日に弱ってない？
続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
よく続くな ３時起き
I'm surprised he can
keep getting up at 3 AM.
It's been more than a week already.
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
もう１週間以上たつよね
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 反比例[はんぴれい]:inverse proportion, 痩せる[やせる]:to become thin/to lose weight|to be barren
何か あいつ 豚と反比例して痩せていってるべ
His weight's kind of going the
opposite direction of the pigs.
Hey.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
こら やめろって 豚丼
Stop it, Pork Bowl.
あれ？
Huh?
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
あっ こっちか 豚丼
Oh, this one's Pork Bowl.
何か…
Are you...
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
みんなと変わらなくね？
...the same as the others now?
Oh, you're 90 kilos now!
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
あっ ９０ｋｇに乗った
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of)
ってことは１週間で９ｋｇか
So you gained nine kilos in one week.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
１日１ｋｇ以上
That means more than a kilo per day.
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, すげー:incredible/unbelievable
豚ってすげー！
Pigs are amazing!
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply
豚は３ｋｇ食って １ｋｇ増えるといわれてるからな
They say pigs gain a kilo
per three kilos consumed.
The liquid feed seems to have worked.
効く[きく]:to be effective|to do its work|to be possible to use
水溶き 効いたようだな
格付け[かくづけ, かくずけ]:rating/classification/allocation
格付けは？
What about his grade?
いかん:Italian warship, いかん:ancient headgear showing rank, 堅い[かたい]:hard|stiff|strong||
上とまではいかんが 中は堅いだろう
He won't quite make
it to premium grade,
but medium grade should be a cinch.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 出荷[しゅっか]:shipping/outgoing freight/forwarding
そろそろ 出荷できそうだな
They're almost ready for send-off.
豚肉[ぶたにく, とんにく]:pork, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
豚肉食べるなんて当たり前のことなのに
We eat pork all the time...
Is it because I know him
that I feel conflicted about it?
もやもや:hazy/murky|gloomy
あいつのこと知ってるからもやもやすんのか
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
食えんのか
Can I eat him?
H-H-Hey!
危[き]:danger|Chinese "rooftop" constellation (one of the 28 mansions)
危っ！
大丈夫？
You okay?
ずり落ちる[ずりおちる]:to slip down/to slide down/to glide down
ずり落ちただけだ 大丈夫
I just slid off. I'm fine!
Hachiken-kun, you should
stop for the day.
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
八軒君 今日はもう乗らない方がいい
What?
考え事[かんがえごと]:something to think about/one's thoughts/concern, ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 集中力[しゅうちゅうりょく]:(powers of) concentration/ability to concentrate
考え事ばかりして集中力のないときに
I can't let you ride a horse when
you are lost in your thoughts
and are unable to focus.
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
馬に乗せるわけにはいきません
It's dangerous,
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, 失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
危ないですし 馬にも失礼です
and it's being rude to the horse.
すいません
Sorry.
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
八軒 元気ないね
Hachiken's kind of down.
ですね
Yeah, he is.
I wonder if something
happened over the summer.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday
夏休み中に何かあったのかな？
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), バイト:work (esp. part time or casual)
御影んちでずっとバイトしてたんでしょ？
He was working at your place
over the break, right?
Yes, he was.
そうですけど
Did something happen between you two?
あんたたち何かあったの？
Nothing at all.
何もないです
へたれ:incompetence/laziness|good-for-nothing
八軒はへたれだねぇ
Hachiken's such a wuss!
ひどい:cruel/heartless|violent
そしてあんたはひどい女だねぇ
And you're so cold!
Huh?! What do you mean, Senpai?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
えっ！？ 何ですか 先輩
Good job!
お疲れさま[おつかれさま]:thank you/many thanks|that's enough for today
お疲れさまですー
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
お疲れ
You, too.
Aki, are you going to
the festival this weekend?
土日[どにち]:weekend/Saturday and Sunday, 祭る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray
アキは土日のお祭り行く？
お祭り[おまつり]:festival/feast/carnival
お祭り？
Festival?
It's at Midorigaoka Park.
公園[こうえん]:(public) park
緑が丘公園の
There will be a lot of stalls.
屋台[やたい]:cart (esp. a food cart)|festival float|stage prop fashioned after a large building||, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full
屋台いっぱい出るって
う～ん どうしよっかなー
I'm not sure...
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
お疲れ
Good job.
お疲れさま[おつかれさま]:thank you/many thanks|that's enough for today
お疲れさまっす
You, too.
お祭り[おまつり]:festival/feast/carnival
八軒もお祭り行かない？
Hachiken, want to come
to a festival, too?
Festival?
祭り[まつり]:festival/feast
祭り？
Yeah!
灰色[はいいろ]:grey/gray/ashen, 農高[のうこう]:agricultural high school, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 思い出[おもいで]:memories/recollections/reminiscence, つくる:to make/to produce|to prepare (food)
そう！ 灰色の農高生活の中で夏の思い出をつくりに！
Let's go create a beautiful
summer memory
despite our grey and dreary
agricultural high school life!
A summer memory...
夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 思い出[おもいで]:memories/recollections/reminiscence
夏の…思い出…
Lost
Deer (Dead)
Bear (Dead)
Bro
Spilt Milk
Wait, what?
えぐる:to gouge/to hollow out|to greatly perturb
えっ！？ 何！？ 私何かえぐった！？
Did I say something wrong?
Hachiken-kun, let's all go to the
festival for a change of pace!
気分転換[きぶんてんかん]:change of pace/change of mood/(mental) break (e.g. going for a walk)
八軒君 気分転換にさ
祭る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray
みんなでお祭り行こうよ ねっ
Okay?
Ooezo Summer Festival
Yeah!
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
うっひょ～ 何から食おっかなー
What should I eat first?
Hachiken, you earned some
money from working, right?
バイト:work (esp. part time or casual), 稼ぐ[かせぐ]:to earn (income)|to score (points, victory)|to work hard (at one's job)
八軒 バイトで稼いだんだろ
おごる:to give (someone) a treat|to be extravagant/to live luxuriously
おごってくれよ
Buy me something!
What?!
えっ！？
Oh? Hachi, you rich now?
金持ち[かねもち]:rich person
おっ？ ハチ 今金持ちなの？
I can't!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
駄目だ こんな所では使えない
I can't spend it here.
Why?
おごる:to give (someone) a treat|to be extravagant/to live luxuriously
何でだよー！ ケチー！ ブー！ おごれよー！
Cheapskate!
Boo!
Come on!
Didn't you guys work?
バイト:work (esp. part time or casual)
お前こそバイトとかしなかったのかよ
Of course!
したよ
I helped out a ton at home
and got an allowance!
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 手伝い[てつだい]:helper/assistant|help, まくる:to turn up/to roll up (e.g. sleeves)|to do relentlessly, 小遣い[こづかい, こずかい]:pocket money/spending money/pin money, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
家の手伝いしまくって小遣いもらったよ
おしゃれ:smartly dressed/stylish|someone smartly dressed, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
でもぜ～んぶおしゃれに使ってしまいました～
But I spent it all on fashion...
お金[おかね]:money, 使い方[つかいかた]:way to use something/treatment/management (of help), 残念[ざんねん]:deplorable/bad luck/regret
お金の使い方の残念な人だ
The way he spends money
is unfortunate...
The Ezonoo brats are back this year!
ことし:this year, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
ことしも来やがったぞ エゾノーのがきどもが！
食べ盛り[たべざかり]:growing child's hearty appetite, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party
食べ盛りの上に労働で腹減らしてるからなぁ
They're still growing,
and they're starving from work!
Damn beasts...
野獣[やじゅう]:beast/monster/wild animal, もめる:to disagree/to dispute/to fight (over)
野獣どもめ
見事[みごと]:splendid|praiseworthy act|utter (esp. defeat), 腹を満たす[はらをみたす]:to satisfy one's appetite
見事やつらの腹を満たしてくれるわ
Just watch, we'll fill you all up!
You know the drill.
分かってるだろうな
Our motto is, "leave no food uneaten."
合言葉[あいことば]:password/watchword|motto, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
合言葉は「残さずきちんと食べましょう」だ
Yeah!
う～っす！
Octopus dumplings, obliterated!
Sold Out
たこ焼き[たこやき, タコやき]:octopus dumplings, 撃破[げきは]:crushing
たこ焼き 撃破！
Yakisoba, obliterated!
Sold Out
焼きそば[やきそば, ヤキソバ]:yakisoba/fried noodles, usu. with with vegetables and meat, 撃破[げきは]:crushing
焼きそば 撃破！
Okonomiyaki, obliterated!
Sold Out
お好み焼き[おこのみやき]:okonomiyaki/savoury pancake containing meat or seafood and vegetables, 撃破[げきは]:crushing
お好み焼き 撃破！
Targeted eradication
of all the carbs!
炭水化物[たんすいかぶつ]:carbohydrate, 系[けい]:system|corollary|system (range of strata that correspond to a particular time period)|, ピンポイント:pinpoint, 根こそぎ[ねこそぎ]:root and branch/thoroughly/by the roots
炭水化物系をピンポイントで根こそぎに！
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 生[き]:pure/undiluted/raw, 生[なま]:raw|natural|unprotected (i.e. not wearing a condom)||, 鬼[おに, き]:oni|spirit of a deceased person|ogre-like person (i.e. fierce, relentless, merciless, etc.)||
他の客のことを考えないなんてエゾノー生は鬼よ！
No consideration for other customers,
those Ezonoo demons!
Hey!
何という[なんという, なんとゆう]:how (beautiful, etc.), ひどい:cruel/heartless|violent, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
こら！ お前たち何というひどい食べ方をしている！
How dare you guys eat like that?!
食品[しょくひん]:food/food products/foodstuffs, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 稲田[いなだ]:paddy field/rice field, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ハッ！ 食品科の稲田先輩！
Inada-senpai, from the food
processing department!
Oh? Looks like Ezonoo has
someone with a conscience.
生[き]:pure/undiluted/raw, 生[なま]:raw|natural|unprotected (i.e. not wearing a condom)||, 良心[りょうしん]:conscience, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target
おっ！？ エゾノー生の中にも良心的なやつがいるようだぞ！
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
そうだ！ 他の客のことも考えろって言ってやれ！
Right on! Tell them to think
of the other customers, too!
Don't just eat carbs!
炭水化物[たんすいかぶつ]:carbohydrate, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, 栄養[えいよう]:nutrition/nourishment, バランス:balance, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 尽くす[つくす]:to exhaust|to devote|to do to exhaustion, なさる:to do
炭水化物ばっかりでなく栄養バランスよく食べ尽くしなさい！
Eat everything,
but maintain a balanced diet!
おっす！
Roger!
Yakitori, obliterated!
焼き鳥[やきとり]:yakitori/chicken pieces (or sometimes beef or pork offal) grilled on a skewer, 撃破[げきは]:crushing
焼き鳥 撃破！
Apple candy, obliterated!
リンゴ:apple (fruit), 撃破[げきは]:crushing
リンゴあめ 撃破！
Curry, obliterated!
カレー:curry, 撃破[げきは]:crushing
カレー 撃破！
Chocolate-covered bananas, obliterated!
チョコ:chocolate, バナナ:banana, 撃破[げきは]:crushing
チョコバナナ 撃破！
食い物[くいもの]:food/foodstuff|prey, 屋台[やたい]:cart (esp. a food cart)|festival float|stage prop fashioned after a large building||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 壮絶[そうぜつ]:grand/heroic/sublime
食い物屋台の方は壮絶だな
The food stalls are sure
looking grim.
ことし:this year, 食い物[くいもの]:food/foodstuff|prey, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 正解[せいかい]:correct/right/correct interpretation (answer, solution)
ことしは食い物やめて正解だったぜ
I'm glad I decided not
to do food this year.
やる
Here.
わーい！
Yay!
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
しっかし みんなよく食うよなー
Man... Everyone sure eats a ton.
寮[りょう]:hostel/dormitory|bureau (government department beneath a ministry under the ritsuryo system), 寮[つかさ]:office|chief|(Yaeyama Islands in Okinawa) person (usually a woman) whose duty it is to officiate at religions ceremonies, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 晩ご飯[ばんごはん]:dinner/evening meal
寮に帰ったら晩ご飯あるのにね
Yeah, even though there will
be dinner back at the dorm.
Feeling better?
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
元気出た？
うん？
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
何か元気なかったからさ
You were kind of down,
so I thought you might feel better
if you had something good to eat.
おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
おいしいもの食べたら元気になるかなって
ありがと:Thank you
あ…ありがとな
Thanks.
You're doing a lot for
Pork Bowl, aren't you?
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
頑張ってるよね 豚丼のこと
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
できることは全部やっときたくて
I just want to make sure I'm
doing everything I can.
もやもや:hazy/murky|gloomy, でかい:huge/big/gargantuan
でも…何かやる前よりもやもやがでかくなってんだよな
But... for some reason,
I'm even more hesitant than before.
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 家畜[かちく]:domestic animals/livestock/cattle, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have
豚丼は家畜で人間が食うために飼ってんだって
Pork Bowl's a farm animal
who's raised to be eaten.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
最初から頭じゃ全部分かってんだよ
I knew all that from the start.
割り切れる[わりきれる]:to be divisible (by)/to be divided without residue (remainder)|to be satisfied, じたばた:(kick and) struggle/wriggle
でも 割り切れなくてじたばたしてるうちに
But I'm still struggling to
come to terms with it all,
出荷[しゅっか]:shipping/outgoing freight/forwarding, 目前[めさき]:before one's eyes|immediate (e.g. interests)|foresight|, 目前[もくぜん]:before one's very eyes/under one's nose/imminence
もう出荷目前になっててさ
and it's almost time to send him off.
焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered, っつー:meaning/called/said
焦るっつーか…
It's kind of frustrating.
あっ でも 大丈夫！
Oh, but I'm okay!
誘う[さそう, いざなう]:to invite/to ask|to tempt, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
ほら 今日誘ってもらって元気出たから
See? Today, I'm better now that
you invited me to come out.
来場[らいじょう, らいば]:attendance, 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 案内[あんない]:information/guidance|to guide, いたす:to do
ご来場の皆さまにご案内いたします
We have an announcement
for everyone here.
公園[こうえん]:(public) park, 中央[ちゅうおう]:centre/center|metropolis, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 丸焼き[まるやき]:whole roast (e.g. pig, turkey, etc.), 提供[ていきょう]:offer/tender/program sponsoring, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
公園中央にて豚の丸焼きをご提供させていただきます
We have a whole roasted pig
in the middle of the park.
Please have a taste.
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 味わう[あじわう]:to taste|to appreciate|to taste, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
皆さん ぜひ味わってください
Awesome!
I know!
ベジタリアン:vegetarian, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
そうだ！ ベジタリアンになってしまえば悩まなくて済むのでは！？
Maybe I won't be conflicted
if I become a vegetarian!
Want a beef kebab?
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 串[くし]:spit/skewer|proxy (computer server), 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
牛串食べる？
Yum!
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
うまい！
でしょ
Right?
ベジタリアン:vegetarian
俺 ベジタリアンなれない…
I can't become a vegetarian...
Oh, a whole roasted pig!
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 丸焼き[まるやき]:whole roast (e.g. pig, turkey, etc.)
おっ！ 豚の丸焼き！
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 匂い[におい]:odour/odor|aura
うまそうな匂いだな
Sure smells awesome.
There's always room for that!
丸焼き[まるやき]:whole roast (e.g. pig, turkey, etc.), 別腹[べつばら]:dessert stomach/having room for dessert despite being full
丸焼きは別腹だよな
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 丸焼き[まるやき]:whole roast (e.g. pig, turkey, etc.), 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
八軒は豚の丸焼き食べねえの？
Hachiken, you're not gonna
have any roasted pig?
Don't need.
いらん
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy, じゃん:isn't it
何だよ 元気ねえじゃん
What's with the long face?
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, もやもや:hazy/murky|gloomy, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
豚丼のことでもやもやしてんのに食えるかよ
How can I eat when I'm
conflicted about Pork Bowl?
You're still conflicted?
悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled
まだ悩んでんの？
世話[せわ]:looking after/help/aid, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), じゃん:isn't it
世話したら何か見えてくるかもって言ってたじゃん
You said you might figure something
out if you took care of him.
ますます:increasingly/more and more/decreasingly (when declining), 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
ますます見えなくなってきた
I'm even more confused now...
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
何だ そりゃ
What do you mean?
だってさ
Well, he dug into the food and got all fat,
but he'll get turned into meat.
がつがつ:greedily/burning with desire for something, 餌[えさ, え]:(animal) feed/fodder|bait, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 太る[ふとる]:to grow fat (stout, plump)/to become fat/to gain weight, 肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||
がつがつ餌食べて太ったと思ったら肉にされて
生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
こいつの生まれてきた意味って何なんだろうって
Makes me wonder why he was even born.
あ～！ もうどうしよう？
Man, what to do?
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||
お前 こん中で一番頭いいんだから
You're the smartest one here!
振る[ふる]:to wave|to sprinkle|to cast (actor)||, 振る[ぶる]:assuming the air of .../behaving like ...|to put on airs
俺たちに振るなよ
Don't ask us!
He's still tied up in
knots over that pig?
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, もんもん:worrying endlessly/anguishedly
あいつ まだ豚のことでもんもんとしてるのか？
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 切り替える[きりかえる]:to change/to exchange/to convert
さっさと気持ち切り替えればいいのにな
He should just change gears already.
根[ね]:root (of a plant)|root (of a tooth, hair, etc.)|root (of all evil, etc.)||, 根[こん]:stick-to-itiveness|radical (esp. one that tends to ionize easily)|root|, 真面目[しんめんもく, しんめんぼく]:one's true character/one's true self|seriousness, 真面目[まじめ]:diligent/serious/honest
根が真面目なんだろ
He's just the type to
take things seriously.
Then he'll have a tough time
getting through this school.
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 学校[がっこう]:school, つらい:painful/bitter|tough
あんなんじゃ この学校でやってくのつらいだろうに
そうか？
Really?
スルー:ignoring/looking the other way/letting pass
分かったふりしてスルーすることだってできるはずなんだよ
He could just pretend to deal with it,
to get himself through school.
But instead, he takes it seriously
それなのに
真面目[しんめんもく, しんめんぼく]:one's true character/one's true self|seriousness, 真面目[まじめ]:diligent/serious/honest, 受け止める[うけとめる]:to catch/to stop the blow|to react to
あいつは真面目に受け止めて
and is honest about it with
the people around him.
周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 真面目[しんめんもく, しんめんぼく]:one's true character/one's true self|seriousness, 真面目[まじめ]:diligent/serious/honest, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
周りにも真面目に返してる
I noticed it during
the pizza thing, too,
ピザのときもそうだったけど
but when someone's serious
about what he does,
真面目[しんめんもく, しんめんぼく]:one's true character/one's true self|seriousness, 真面目[まじめ]:diligent/serious/honest, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble
真面目にやってるといつの間にか人が集まってくるんだよな
people just naturally flock to him.
価値観[かちかん]:sense of values/values/value system, 凝り固まる[こりかたまる]:to coagulate|to be fanatical|to stiffen, 群れ[むれ]:group/crowd/flock
価値観が凝り固まっている群れに
By having a foreign
body like Hachiken
thrown into a lot full
of indoctrinated sheep,
異物[いぶつ]:foreign substance|strange object|dead body, 交ざる[まざる]:to be mixed/to be blended with/to associate with, ことによる:depending on the circumstances|due to (with modifying verb)
八軒のような異物が交ざることによって
普段[ふだん]:usual/habitual/ordinary, ディスカッション:discussion, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
普段やらないようなディスカッションが起こっている
atypical discussions are taking place.
The flock evolves when they are joined
by someone with different values.
価値観[かちかん]:sense of values/values/value system, 交ざる[まざる]:to be mixed/to be blended with/to associate with, 群れ[むれ]:group/crowd/flock, 進化[しんか]:evolution/progress
価値観の違う者が交ざれば群れは進化する
The dairy science first-years are
turning into an interesting lot.
酪農[らくのう]:dairy (farm), 科学[かがく]:science, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
１年酪農科学科 面白くなってきたな
公園[こうえん]:(public) park, 冬[ふゆ]:winter
この公園 冬は氷祭りやるんだよ
There's an ice festival
at this park in winter.
Yeah?
へえー
The ice sculptures are
really beautiful.
氷[こおり]:ice|shaved ice (usually served with flavored simple syrup), 氷[ひ]:ice|hail, 彫刻[ちょうこく]:carving/engraving/sculpture, 奇麗[きれい, キレイ]:pretty|clean|completely
氷の彫刻が奇麗なんだよね
Let's come again with everyone.
またみんなで来ようよ
いいね 来よう
Good idea! Let's do that.
I'll come, too.
俺も 俺も
You'll get kicked out before winter.
冬[ふゆ]:winter, 退学[たいがく]:dropping out of school|expulsion from school|leaving school (university, etc.) after completing a course
常盤は冬までに退学になるなよ
うるせえ！
Shut up!
兄貴[あにき, アニキ]:elder brother|one's senior|older man
あっ！ 兄貴！
Oh.
Bro?!
Hey, Yuugo, Mikage-chan!
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
おう！ 勇吾に御影ちゃん
何やってんだよ
What're you doing here?!
屋台[やたい]:cart (esp. a food cart)|festival float|stage prop fashioned after a large building||, バイト:work (esp. part time or casual), 食費[しょくひ]:food expense, 浮く[うく]:to float|to become merry|to become loose||
屋台でバイト中 食費浮くし
Helping out a stall. Food's free, too.
生[き]:pure/undiluted/raw, 生[なま]:raw|natural|unprotected (i.e. not wearing a condom)||
そっか エゾノー生来てたのか
So Ezonoo students are here, huh?
どうり:reason/logic/sense, 買い出し[かいだし]:going out to shop/going shopping|buying in quantity, ばっか:only/merely|approximately, やらす:to allow/to let (somebody) do/to make (somebody) do
どうりで買い出しばっかやらされるわけだ
No wonder I'm getting sent
out to buy more food.
Why're you here...
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
何でこんな所で…
I'm happy for you!
よかったな
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun, じゃん:isn't it
友達いっぱいで楽しそうじゃん
You seem to be having a great
time with all your friends.
I'm working at the yakisoba
stall over there.
焼きそば[やきそば, ヤキソバ]:yakisoba/fried noodles, usu. with with vegetables and meat, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, バイト:work (esp. part time or casual)
俺 そこの焼きそば屋でバイトしてっから
Come eat.
食い[くい]:eating|bite (in fishing)
食いに来いよ
安い[やすい]:cheap/inexpensive|calm, してやる:to do for (someone)
ちょっと安くしてやるよ
I'll give you guys a small discount.
Whoa!
うお！ マジっすか！？
Really?!
Hachiken's brother is really generous!
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, 太っ腹[ふとっぱら]:generous/magnanimous/big-hearted
お兄さん太っ腹！
I said small!
ちょっとだけだぞ
You guys aren't coming?
八軒たち 行かねえのか
There won't be anything left!
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
全部食っちゃうぞ～
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
あっ！ いかん！ みんな食うな！
Oh, no!
Nobody eat that!
倒す[たおす]:to throw down|to kill|to overthrow|, 倒す[こかす]:to knock down/to knock over
やったぞ～！ エゾノー倒したぞ～！
We won!
We defeated Ezonoo!
Sorry, guys!
ごめんよ みんなぁ
I think it takes a certain genius
to make horrible yakisoba...
焼きそば[やきそば, ヤキソバ]:yakisoba/fried noodles, usu. with with vegetables and meat, まずい:poor-quality/shoddy|unskillful, まずい:unappetising/unappetizing|unskillful, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 才能[さいのう]:talent/ability
焼きそばをまずく作れるって才能だと思います
照れる[てれる]:to be shy/to be bashful/to feel awkward
いやぁ 照れるな ハハハハ
Aw, you flatter me.
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
朝食[ちょうしょく, あさげ]:breakfast
朝食の時間です
It's time for breakfast.
寮生[りょうせい]:boarder/boarding student, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 食堂[しょくどう]:dining room/dining hall|restaurant, 食堂[じきどう]:dining hall (at a temple), 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
寮生は全員食堂に集まってください
All students, please report
to the dining hall.
Cafeteria
Oh, I smell curry!
カレー:curry, 匂い[におい]:odour/odor|aura
おっ カレーの匂い
We have great curry here.
カレー:curry, おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive
ここのカレー おいしいわよね
だよな
Yeah, seriously.
Huh?
What?
何よ？
No, nothing surprises me anymore.
驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished
いや もう何があっても驚かない
いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
いただきま～す！
Thanks for the food!
Yum!
うまる:to be buried/to be covered|to overflow, やっぱ:too/also|still, カレー:curry, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
うまっ！ やっぱカレーは豚っしょ！
Curry's got to be pork curry!
No, I prefer chicken.
チキン:chicken
いや 俺はチキンがいい
ビーフ:beef
バ～カ ビーフだろ
Idiot, beef is best!
やっぱ:too/also|still, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
う～ん やっぱ豚だな
Nah, pork.
A lot of us prefer pork!
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 派[は]:clique/faction/school
豚派多いな
すき焼き[すきやき, スキヤキ]:sukiyaki/thin slices of beef, cooked with various vegetables in a table-top cast-iron pan, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork
うち すき焼きも豚だぞ
We use pork in our sukiyaki, too.
がっつり:firmly/plentifully/with all one's might, 豚肉[ぶたにく, とんにく]:pork, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
がっつり豚肉食いてえな
Man, I want pork.
Like a pork bowl!
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
豚丼とか
Yum...
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
うまい
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, 手紙[てがみ]:letter, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
たまには手紙を書いてみようよ
ポストカード:postcard, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
どっかにポストカードでもあったけ
懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
懐かしい顔に見けて
ほんの:mere/only/just, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, ノスタルジー:nostalgia
ほんの数行ノスタルジーを
調子[ちょうし]:tune|vein|condition||
調子はどうですか
忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
忙しくしていますか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 具合[ぐあい]:condition/state/manner, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.)
あの夢の具合はどんなだい
気分転換[きぶんてんかん]:change of pace/change of mood/(mental) break (e.g. going for a walk), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
気分転換くらいのノリで
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 歌う[うたう]:to sing|to sing (one's praises in a poem, etc.)/to compose a poem
一緒に歌わないか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
そして無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 続き[つづき]:sequel/continuation/(also suffix) continuation (in time and space), 語り合う[かたりあう]:to talk together
あの夢の続きを語り合おうよ
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
明日は頑張ろうぜ
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
今はそこにある未来へ
駆け出す[かけだす]:to run off/to break into a run/to start running
駆け出して さぁ 行こう
This story is a work of fiction.
The people and groups are fictitious, but the themes relating to food and life are firmly based in reality. Visiting the places and facilities used as models can be dangerous and may result it contracting diseases from the animals. Please enjoy this story as a work of fiction.